So, this course on Software Engineering. Now, we will just have a brief introduction to various
issues in Software Engineering, motivation, why we need to study this course, what are
the benefits that will accrue from here and so on. So, let us get started. First is about
myself, I will be the instructor for this course. My name is Rajip Mal, completed all my
education bachelors, masters, PhD from the Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore that
is quite some years back. That is the institute where I graduated and then worked few years
with Motorola India and then have been with IIT Kharagpur since 1994 and currently a professor
at the CAC department. So, that is the institute Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur.
To start with any course, we need to know what the course deals with, we will also do the
same thing, we will start with the basic definition of Software Engineering. If somebody asks that
what is Software Engineering, we should be able to answer based on this. The simplest
answer, what is Software Engineering is an engineering approach to develop software.
But then the question arises that what exactly is the engineering approach to develop software,
how is it different from traditional approach to develop software. To appreciate this distinction
between the engineering approach to develop software and traditional novice approach to
develop software, we will just look at a analogy with a building construction.
Let us say you want to construct a building, what would you do? First let us consider that you
want to build a small wall like this, that you will be very easily be able to do from your
basic intuition that you need some bricks, cement, color and so on and you will succeed
in developing a good small wall like this. But let us say you are now asked to build
a large building like this having 30, 40 floors a complex. Your basic intuition about construction
will not work here. If you actually get started building this with your basic intuition building
may collapse, it will never complete, it will be of poor quality and so on. The same
thing is with respect to software. If somebody is asked to write a small program let us
say 10, 20, 50 lines of code, he will be able to do it based on his basic intuition. But
let us consider developing a software which is 100,000 lines of code. Now if you wants
to extend the intuition and develop a large software, again you will face the same fate
as constructing a large building from the basic intuition. The engineering approach to develop
software lets one to develop software based on some techniques and tools. So, we will look
at those techniques and tools as part of the software engineering. So, an alternate
definition of software engineering can be that it is a collection of past experience which has
resulted in various techniques for development of large software, methodologies for development
and some guidelines and tools. As we proceed with this course we will be clear about what
are the techniques, what are the methodologies and guidelines, tools and so on.
Now let us look at the IEEE definition of what software engineering is. The IEEE definition
is software engineering is the application of systematic, disciplined, quantifiable approach
to the development, operation and maintenance of software and that is the application of
engineering to software. So, the IEEE definition also says that software
engineering is the engineering approach to develop software and it further elaborates
this by saying application of systematic, disciplined, quantifiable approach and all
developed from experience of programmers over the last several years. To motivate the need
for software engineering why it is important for the software developers to learn software
engineering let us just understand what the software crisis is because everybody says
that there is a software crisis. The software crisis the symptoms are that they fail to meet
user requirements. Software is delivered and then the users feel that it is not what they
wanted. Software is expensive, much more expensive than hardware and every year the
difference between software and hardware prices have been increasing. It is difficult to make
any changes to the software to debug. If there is a problem reported it takes long time to
correct it sometimes the bugs cannot be corrected. Difficult to enhance add new features it
is very usual for software to be delivered late and use resources non-optimally. For most
of the software that you order or develop as part of project have these symptoms that
they rarely meet the user requirements turn out to be very expensive, difficult to alter
debug and enhance delivered late and use resources non-optimally.
Just to explain how expensive is the software compared to hardware over the years if we compute
how much a company spent on hardware and how much it spent on software. If we plot the
ratio we will see that 1960s are and so the hardware was the major expense millions of
dollars of hardware and then software was very inexpensive compared to the hardware.
But then the hardware costs have dropped dramatically and software costs have risen. So now the
hardware cost divided by software cost is almost nominal approaching 0. Just to give a feel just
let us say that a laptop or test of costs 45000 rupees and let us say some software let us
say rational. It costs 3 lakh rupees if it is not locked and floating license cost 6
lakh rupees which runs on a desktop. So just see that the cost of one software is many times
the cost of the hardware and then we need to run various types of software on the hardware.
So now the software is much more expensive. Companies spend much more on software than
on hardware. But then the question arises is that why is that the cost of hardware has dropped so
much but then software has not really the cost has not dropped and actually increased.
There are many reasons for this. We will examine the reasons but before that we just
want to ask a very fundamental question that if hardware is so good it is delivered in time
extremely reliable inexpensive then why not have everything in hardware because after all
whatever can be done by software can also be done by hardware. There must be some reasons
otherwise people would only be developing hardware and using it and there would be no software.
Let us look at the reasons why software is indispensable and actually the use of software
is increasing as compared to hardware. There are 2 or 3 major virtues or strong points of
software which actually make it a preferred solution compared to hardware. One of the most
important thing is that developing software is easy, faster and also if you find anything
to be changed you can easily change it hardware development is a long drawn process. If it is
a VLSI chip that you are considering then it is multi-year starting from requirements
to fabrication it is a long process. And if you later want to make a small change
again you have to make that long process change requirements change design mask and so on fabricate
test. So, that is a long duration several years compared to software making a fix a
small change may be just a few days and also software consumes no space weight or power.
If you want to develop something that works in software let us say rational enterprise suit
let us consider any software or maybe let us say the word processing software let us consider
Microsoft word. It is possible to have this developed in hardware, but then the size of
the hardware will be enormous. It will be extremely expensive and it will consume huge power,
but then if you as software it just resides in your hard disk and just gets executed
feature by feature and that is the reason why software is the preferred mode of solution for
applications as compared to hardware. But then one thing we need to appreciate that software
is becoming more complex and as we change software it also the complexity increases.
But then what is the basic reason? We are trying to answer some fundamental questions here and as
we proceed these questions are actually the basics based on which the other techniques are built up
must understand these basic principles that the more complex is the software the harder it
is to change and also if we change it the complexity of the software further increases.
What is the reason? The main reason is that to change a software we must first understand it
without understanding how it works where exactly we have to change we cannot change it
and if it is very complex software will take lot of effort to understand and then make the
change and also if we make a small change it changes the basic underlying design modularity
and so on as we will see later that every change actually degrades the structure of
the software and makes it much more complex for somebody else to understand as changes
keep on happening to a software may be due to additional features to be supported may be
to correct bugs and so on the software becomes more complex becomes much more difficult for
somebody to understand and make further changes. This is one of the very basic principles as
we proceed will need these principles and it will help us understand why some techniques
are the way that they are. Now let us look at the large number of projects
that are done what is the statistics about the success rate of the projects. The success
rate is very surprising that only a quarter is successful just 28% is successful a quarter
is never sees the light of the day they are cancelled and half of the projects they
are delayed delivered run delivered late and also the cost overrun the price increases.
But then why is it that only quarter of the software is actually successful half of the
software is challenged and another quarter is actually failure they are to be cancelled.
Let us try to understand what is the reason the reasons are that now there is a demand
for more and more software. The hardware is simpler and the software is much more complex
due to obvious reason that any complexity in the application has to be done in the software
because otherwise hardware will be very difficult to develop it will be large it will consume
lots of power volume and so on. So, the problem sizes of software is increasing
year after year poor project management because these are after all entirely manual efforts
the programmers have to develop they have to write the code test and so on.
But surprisingly one of the major reasons that has been identified for the software crisis
is the lack of adequate training in software engineering. The developers they are not
very convergent with the latest software engineering techniques. When they graduate
from a college they do not have proper background in software engineering they have studied
some things that that do not really help in developing good quality software. There is a
increasing skill shortage as far as software development software engineering principles
are concerned and even with software engineering the skill improvements are not really very
drastic it improves moderately very slowly over the years compared to the way the
problem sizes are increasing the productivity development has not really kept pace.
Let us just try to understand another very basic aspect might have heard that somebody
saying programming is an art, but then we said software engineering and there is
an engineering approach to develop software. So, is software an art or engineering let
us just try to understand the issues concerned. Now let us look at how the technology develops
for any specific domain whether it is steel making whether it is paper making let us see
how the technology develops. If we look at the technology development pattern initially
somebody comes up with some idea and then follows it comes up with solution. Let us say paper
making was known to some people in China and only they could develop good quality paper.
The others tried they do not know how to make paper possibly came up with some very bad
quality paper and they thought that paper making is an art. And artist as you know that if you ask
somebody that how come he paints so well let us say an artist is a draws a nice drawing and you
ask him how did you come up with such a nice drawing you will say that ok it just comes
to me I just draw it like that. Same thing with technology initially they say that we
just know how to make it, but then slowly the art form in technology development graduates
to a craft form. In a craft form there are some techniques they can identify how they make it
and they do not share it actually with lot of people they share with only their apprentice.
It is basically a hidden secret let us say paper making or steel making they would not like to
share with many people they know the techniques, but they do not share it and there are craftsmen
who know how to do it. So, they are basically the apprentices and then they also share with
very less number of people. And slowly it transits to an engineering approach. In engineering the
techniques are all investigated the past experience is analyzed and scientific basis is given to
these techniques. These are well documented and this can be studied by anybody these are open
knowledge and then it has graduated into engineering. But what about program writing? Yes it is same
pattern the program writing has followed. In the 1960s there were good programmers and there were
bad programmers. The good programmers they just wrote good programs and they do not know
how they write good programs, but then they just wrote good programs and the other programmers
they just struggled and could not come up with good programs. But then slowly the techniques
that they were using in writing the good programs were identified and shared with few and that
was the craft form that good programmers could train other programmers who can become
good programmers. But later the techniques that they were using for writing good programs
were all systematically investigated scientific basis given to them and published in the literature
in the book form and so on. So, that anybody can read and then it has graduated to an
engineering firm where somebody can read what are required to really develop good software
large software the basic principles one need to know and so on and our focus is looking
at this software engineering techniques. If we look at the engineering approach to
develop software there is heavy use of past experience the past experience is systematically
arranged and for this experience investigation has been made theoretical basis and quantifiable
techniques quantitative techniques have been provided, but then for many of the techniques
that has come from experience quantitative techniques have not been provided could not
be provided and these are just thumb rules. There is tradeoff between alternatives because
when we design a software we have to look at various kinds of tradeoff the complexity
of the software the cost and so on. And because of the tradeoff between alternatives
we have a pragmatic approach to cost effectiveness. Just to summarize our discussion software engineering
is actually an engineering approach to develop software and this engineering approach has
developed from past experience of large number of programmers. Over the years the programmers
have innovated new ways of looking at how to write program good programs and so on. All
these techniques have been systematically organized so that somebody can go through these topics
and be a good programmer be able to write large programs in a team and so on. So, that
is the focus of our discussion and over the next few lectures we will discuss various
techniques issues and so on. Thank you.